{"tossups": [{"question": "This leader\u2019s top generals included Atoc and Quizquiz. Because of his religious beliefs, this man pleaded with his captors to be killed by strangulation rather than to be burned alive; ironically, to ensure that happened, he converted to Catholicism shortly before his death, which was ordered by Vincente de Valverde. This man o\u21b5ered a ransom of a large room filled once with gold and twice with silver after he was captured at Cajamarca. Francisco Pizarro ordered the execution of, for the point, what final Incan emperor?", "answer": "<b> Atahualpa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this battle, an attack by Ulu\u00b8c Ali [ool-ooch Ali] succeeded in capturing the flag of the Knights of Malta. This battle was followed up by a peace treaty negotiated by Alvise I of Venice and a Spanish attack on Tunisia. In this battle, which came after the fall of the Cypriot stronghold of Famagusta, galleasses proved e\u21b5ective against a fleet of galleys led by Ali Pasha. For the point, name this decisive 1571 naval battle in which Don John led a European alliance to defeat an Ottoman incursion into the Mediterranean.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Lepanto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s first President failed to retire in 1992, as popular support demanded he run again; that leader, Dawda Jawara, was overthrown in a coup in 1994. Recent conflict in this country was averted when Ousman Badjie refused to commit his troops. In January, longtime strongman Yahya Jammeh refused to leave power in this country, prompting a military intervention from neighboring Senegal. Adama Barrow was recently elected president of, for the point, what West African Islamic Republic with capital at Banjul?", "answer": "the<b> Gambia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Bob Novak and Rowland Evans described how this practice could last \u201cten minutes or four hours.\u201dA biography by Robert Caro extensively covers this practice, which often took place in swimming pools and cloakrooms and was used extensively while its originator tried to get bills passed while serving as the so-called \u201cMaster of the Senate.\u201d A photograph of this practice shows its user looming over Senator Theodore Green from less than a foot away in 1957. For the point, name this aggressive tactic used by Lyndon Johnson to coerce others.", "answer": "the Lyndon Johnson<b> Treatment</b> (accept additional information; prompt on descriptive answers of Lyndon Johnson\u2019s coercive tactics until his name is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A telegram sent prior to this battle noted \u201cWeather today fine, but high waves.\u201d To avoid capture after this battle, the crew of the<em> Nikolai I</em> scuttled her on Dokdo Island. At the end of this battle, Admiral Nebogatov surrendered rather than doom his 2,000-plus sailors; regardless, his fleet had lost six battleships and twenty-eight other ships in a single day after eight months of sailing from the Baltic Sea. Admiral Togo \u201ccrossed the Russian T\u201d at, for the point, what decisive May 1905 battle that essentially ended the Russo-Japanese War?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tsushima</b> Strait(s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this State Department official who, in 1950, was convicted of being a Communist.", "answer": "Alger<b> Hiss</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This saint was posthumously exonerated by Pope Callixtus III, and Bishop Pierre Cauchon was excommunicated for persecuting this saint. This saint was captured near Compi`egne, found guilty of heresy, and burned at the stake in 1431. For the point, name this patron saint of France who broke the Siege of Orleans during the Hundred Years War.", "answer": "<b> Joan of Arc</b> (or<b> Jean d\u2019Arc</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The philosopher Christine Korsgaard is best known for her reinvigoration of this man\u2019s thoughts. This man used a \u201ctranscendental method\u201d to avoid many common problems of metaphysics. This philosopher first elucidated the theory of democratic peace based upon his belief that a kingdom of ends represented the highest ideal of human society. The distinctions between analytic and synthetic propositions, as well as<em> a priori</em> and<em> a posteriori</em> propositions, were first developed by this German idealist. For the point, name this 18th-century moral philosopher and author of<em> Critique of Pure Reason</em>.", "answer": "Immanuel<b> Kant</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In this city, Helen Hall was shot by a sniper in the Harlan House Motel; later that day, three black teenagers were killed in this city\u2019s Algiers Motel by National Guardsmen looking for other snipers. The Guard had been ordered into this city to put down a riot that was sparked by a police raid on a \u201cblind pig\u201d drinking party on 12th Street, an order made by Governor George Romney. Outfielder Willie Horton begged rioters in this city to go home shortly after leaving a game in Tiger Stadium. 43 people died in 1967 riots in, for the point, what highly-segregated Michigan city?", "answer": "<b> Detroit</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Lawrence Veiller produced an exhibition named after these types of buildings. People are seen leaning their heads out of these types of buildings in a photo titled<em> Bandit\u2019s Roost</em>. These sorts of buildings, which were common in rookeries, often featured incredibly narrow airshafts between two of their \u201cdumbbell\u201dtype. Jacob Riis took many photographs of these buildings, which were federally required by an 1867 act to have one toilet per twenty people. For the point, name these often poorly ventilated apartment complexes.", "answer": "<b> tenement</b>s (prompt on apartment buildings and other generic terms before mentioned; do not accept or prompt on projects)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Photography"}, {}, {"question": "This empire was visited by Zhou Daguan, who mistakenly believed that a Buddha statue existed at this empire\u2019s West Mebon site. A gallery at this empire\u2019s Bayon temple reveals how this empire\u2019s ships engaged the forces of the Champa kingdom on the Tonle Sap lake. This empire\u2019s<em> barays</em>, or water tanks, are speculated to symbolize the Sea of Creation. A temple dedicated to Vishnu was built in the image of Mount Meru during the reign of this empire\u2019s Suryavarman II. Angkor Wat was built by, for the point, what long-lasting Cambodian empire?", "answer": "<b> Khmer</b> Empire (do not accept or prompt on Khmer Rouge)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This oration was preceded by a drunken speech in which the vice president could be heard asking\u201cWhat is the name of the secretary of the navy?\u201d This oration asks listeners to \u201cjudge not, that we be not judged\u201d after pondering why men dare ask \u201ca just God\u2019s assistance in wringing their bread from the sweat\u201d of others. In accordance with the speaker\u2019s lenient \u201cTen-Percent\u201d plan for the readmission of Confederate states, this oration advocates for \u201cmalice toward none\u201d and \u201ccharity towards all.\u201d For the point, name this speech, given on March 4, 1865 by a successfully re-elected President.", "answer": "Abraham<b> Lincoln\u2019s second inaugural</b> address (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One figure during this period was confined to the Antoniev Monastery until he was freed and made into a religious head. During this period, Jacob de la Gardie\u2019s forces were destroyed by a cavalry charge at the Battle of Klushino. Marina Mniszech [MI-sheck] fought to have her two husbands crowned as Dmitry during this period with the support of Poland-Lithuania. The brief reign of Boris Godunov began, for the point, what period of turmoil in Russia that was ended by the ascension of the Romanov dynasty?", "answer": "<b> Time of Troubles</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A second century AD text about this ruler\u2019s life opens with stories of his teacher, Upagupta, and of his previous life as Jaya, a boy who met the Buddha. This ruler defeated the Utkala in modern day Odisha, killing 200,000 soldiers and civilians according to a series of inscriptions on boulders and pillars throughout his empire. After winning the aforementioned Kalinga War, this son of Bindusara renounced violence and converted to Buddhism. For the point, name this third century BC Mauryan ruler.", "answer": "<b> Ashoka</b> the Great (or<b> Asoka</b> or<b> Ashok</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this war, the 18th Mechanized Brigade was wiped out in minutes because of a decisive assault and poor visibility conditions in the Battle of 73 Easting. An important action early in this war was the use of air strikes to drive back an attack on the city of Khafji. Northern and southern no-fly zones were established at the 32nd and 36th parallels after this war, in which the losing side\u2019s retreating columns were decimated in the Highway of Death. For the point, name this 1991 war in which coalition forces liberated Kuwait from Iraqi control.", "answer": "First<b> Gulf</b> War (accept<b> Kuwait</b> War; accept<b> First Iraq War</b>; do not accept or prompt on\u201cIraq War\u201d alone; prompt on Operation Desert Storm and/or Operation Desert Shield)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this event, \u201cJohn Johnson\u201d aroused suspicions when he claimed that the firewood he owned belonged to Thomas Percy. During the siege of Holbeche House at this event\u2019s conclusion, the perpetrator Thomas Wintour was captured. A letter of warning sent to Lord Monteagle thwarted this event, which was planned by Roger Catesby. For the point, name this event, annually commemorated on November 5, in which a group of conspirators including Guy Fawkes attempted to blow up James I\u2019s parliament.", "answer": "<b> Gunpowder Plot</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a novel, an adviser to this monarch employs Lady Rochfort to obtain testimony against a rival queen. A play set during the reign of this monarch is narrated by the Common Man. The reign of this monarch is the subject of Hilary Mantel\u2019s novels<em> Bring Up the Bodies</em> and<em> Wolf Hall</em> and of Robert Bolt\u2019s play<em> A Man for All Seasons</em>. During this king\u2019s rule, Thomas Cromwell led the persecution of Sir Thomas More. For the point, name this monarch whose several marriages were the subject of Ford Maddox Ford\u2019s <em>The Fifth Queen</em>.", "answer": "<b> Henry VIII</b> [eight]", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "On this island in 1930, Mona Rudao led a revolt of indigenous Seedig forces against colonial Japanese authorities in Wushe. In 1662, the Pescadores were a staging ground for an invasion of this island by Koxinga, who conquered its colonial outposts, including Fort Zeelandia. The Treaty of Shimonoseki gave Japan control of this island in 1895, and the Allies at the 1943 Cairo Conference elected to return this island to Nationalist China. For the point, name this Asian island which, in 1949, became the home of Chiang Kai-Shek\u2019s Kuomintang.", "answer": "<b> Taiwan</b> (or<b> Formosa</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An attempted river crossing led by this commander was thwarted at the Battle of Beauport. This commander led the red division at the Battle of Louisbourg, during which he successfully captured Lighthouse Point. This man\u2019s second-in-command, Robert Monckton, was wounded in a battle that paved the way for George Townshend to accept the surrender of a French colonial stronghold. For the point, name this British general who died with his rival, Louis-Joseph Montcalm, at the Battle of the Plains of Abraham.", "answer": "James<b> Wolfe</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "According to one story, these people stunned Henry of Champagne by jumping o\u21b5a cli\u21b5to prove their loyalty to Rashid Sinan. Their fortresses were destroyed by Kitbuqa, who sacked Alamut shortly after they attempted to kill Mongke Khan. These people, who belonged to the Nizari Ismaili sect of Islam, were trained by an \u201cOld Man of the Mountain\u201d who drugged them with cannabis into thinking they were in paradise. For the point, name this group of 12th century warriors who carried out covert killings and lend their name to the modern practice of killing political leaders.", "answer": "<b> Assassin</b>s (or al-<b>Hashishuun</b> or al-<b>Hashishiin</b>; prompt on (Nizari) Ismalis before mentioned; prompt on (Shi\u2019a) Muslims before mentioned; prompt on Persians)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city briefly captured the Tower of the Flies to gain control of Acre harbor during the War of Saint Sabas. This city almost ended an Aragonese invasion after winning the Battle of Ponza to lift the siege of Gaeta. Its Black Sea colony of Ca\u21b5a may have been the starting point of the Black Plague, and it later lost much of its maritime power in the War of Chioggia [key-oh-jee-ah]. At Lepanto, Andrea Doria led the fleet of, for the point, what rival of Venice and hometown of Christopher Columbus?", "answer": "<b> Genoa</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A person with this name married Juba II of Numidia, and, along with her husband, brought order to the Roman province of Mauretania. The only full sister of Alexander the Great had this name. Antiochus III of Seleucia organized the marriage of his daughter of this name to Ptolemy V. A woman of this name supposedly sneaked into Julius Caesar\u2019s quarters in a carpet, after which she became his mistress; that woman of this name committed suicide in the wake of the Battle of Actium. For the point, identify this name of several Egyptian queens.", "answer": "<b> Cleopatra</b> (accept<b> Cleopatra</b> I Syra; accept<b> Cleopatra</b> of Macedon; accept<b> Cleopatra</b> VII Philopator; accept<b> Cleopatra</b> Selene)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This country lost a ferry named the<em> Hydro</em> while trying to transfer material from its plant at Rjukan. Operation Gunnerside was able to eliminate this country\u2019s stockpile of heavy water, stopping its nuclear weapons program. This country assigned its best fighter pilots to JV 44 to fly the first jet-powered fighter, the Messerschmitt 262.<em> Wunderwa\u21b5e</em>, or wonder weapons, were produced during World War II by, for the point, what country, for whom Wernher von Braun designed the V1 and V2 rockets?", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b> (accept<b> Third Reich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This figure helped three William Seward sold this woman a house in Auburn, New York in 1859. This figure helped three steamboats avoid mines during the Combahee River Raid and later served Robert Gould Shaw his last meal at Fort Wagner. William Lloyd Garrison gave the nickname \u201cMoses\u201d to this figure, who served in an organization that communicated via quilt designs and songs like \u201cFollow the Drinking Gourd.\u201d In April 2016, Jack Lew announced that Andrew Jackson will be replaced on the front of the $20 bill by, for the point, what woman who led the Underground Railroad?", "answer": "Harriet<b> Tubman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1966, three undersea oil tanks were built in this city by the Chicago Bridge and Iron Company, inspiring the name of its Chicago Beach. In 2017, this city\u2019s fire department introduced water jetpacks as a means to quickly reach burning areas. This city contains the Internet City and Media City free zones, as well as the Jebel Ali zone that boasts the largest man-made harbor in the world. Slave labor has driven a construction boom in, for the point, what most populous city of the United Arab Emirates and home of the Burj Khalifa, the world\u2019s tallest building?", "answer": "<b> Dubai</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A one-week war named for this activity began with a bombing raid conducted by passenger aircraft and was fought between El Salvador and Honduras. While performing this activity, Diego Maradona executed a controversial, \u201cmiraculous\u201d feat dubbed the Hand of God. The 2018 and 2022 world championships of this activity will be held in Russia and, controversially, Qatar, thanks to FIFA bribery. For the point, name this sport played by Cristiano Ronaldo and Lionel Messi.", "answer": "<b> soccer</b> (or association<b> football</b>; do not accept American or gridiron football)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In the 12th century, Richard I sold the island of Cyprus to this entity. The Council of Troyes formally endorsed this organization, whose headquarters were at the captured Al-Aqsa Mosque on Temple Mount. The last head of this organization, Jacques de Molay, was executed by Philip IV of France at the behest of Pope Clement V. Members of this organization displayed a red cross while protecting pilgrims. For the point, name this wealthy holy order that fought in the Crusades alongside the Hospitallers.", "answer": "Knights<b> Templar</b>s (accept the<b> Order of Solomon\u2019s Temple</b>; accept<b> Poor Fellow-Soldiers of Christ and of the Temple of Solomon</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This commodity partially titles a historiography by Allan Kuliko\u21b5that argues that its production created a caste system, partially because it involved a gang system rather than a task system. Glasgow merchants who imported this commodity from the American colonies were referred to as its namesake\u201clords.\u201d This primary cash commodity of colonial Virginia and North Carolina was first commercially raised in North America by John Rolfe in the early 1600s. For the point, name this crop whose leaves are used to form cigars.", "answer": "<b> tobacco</b> (accept<b> Tobacco and Slaves</b>; prompt on slaves before \u201cGlasgow\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man invited controversy by increasing the funding of the Maynooth seminary. He chaired the Bullion Committee and brought his country to the gold standard, and he laid the foundations of a modern political party by issuing the Tamworth Manifesto. This man succeeded the Duke of Wellington and oversaw a split in his Conservative Party due to his support of Catholics and the Irish. For the point, name this British prime minister who repealed the Corn Laws and created the first modern police force in London.", "answer": "Robert<b> Peel</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}